<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle sent by Monsievr de Vrillac, advocate in the Parliament of Paris; to Monsievr de Vrillac his father, vpon the occasion of his conuersion. Faithfully translated into English, accoriding to the French copie; By C.C.</title>
            <author>Vrillac, Monsieur de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101817</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837620</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1956</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14583)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1956)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1013:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle sent by Monsievr de Vrillac, advocate in the Parliament of Paris; to Monsievr de Vrillac his father, vpon the occasion of his conuersion. Faithfully translated into English, accoriding to the French copie; By C.C.</title>
                  <author>Vrillac, Monsieur de.</author>
                  <author>C. C., fl. 1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. D[awson] for William Sheffard, and are to be sold at the signe of the starre vnder St Peters-Church in Corne-hill, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by C.C., of a letter written by Monsier de Vrillac.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  EaArly works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1956:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1956:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE SENT BY MON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIEVR de VRILLAC, ADVOCATE IN THE PARLIAMENT of PARIS; To MONSIEVR de VRILLAC his FATHER, vpon <hi>the occaſion of his</hi> Conuerſion.</p>
            <p>Faithfully Tranſlated into Engliſh, according to the French Copie; By C. C.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for WILLIAM SHEFFARD, and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Starre vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peters-Church in Corne-hill, and in Popes-head Alley, 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1956:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1956:2"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE SENT BY MONSIEVR de V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RILLAC, ADVOCATE IN the Parliament of PARIS, To <hi>Monſieur</hi> de <hi>Vrillac</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ther, vpon the occaſion of his Conuerſion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt deare, and my moſt honoured Father and Mother, I ſay the truth in Chriſt I lie not, my Conſcience bearing me witneſſe, that I haue continuall ſorrow and griefe in my heart, that I muſt forſake you, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the world: my griefe being the more for that I know how much my eſtranging my ſelfe from you, will breed you ſorrow and affliction. But this hope haue I in God, that your ſorrow
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1956:3"/> ſhall be turned into ioy, and your affliction into conſolation, when your wiſedomes (void of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and worldly reſpects) ſhall conſider, that the voyage which ſeparates me from you, is to bring me neerer to God, and to ſet my Conſcience at reſt and quiet.</p>
            <p>For I may no longer conceale it from you, that by the often reading and ſerious meditation of the holy Scriptures, together with calling vpon the name of God, the Lord hath ſhewed me that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to ſee on the one ſide the new corrupt errors, ſuperſtitions, and hereſies of the Roman Church, and on the other ſide, the pure truth, taught in thoſe Churches that are purged from the nouelty of Popery, and reformed according to the true Antiquitie of the Apoſtles and Prophets.</p>
            <p>Which knowledge I confeſſe I haue for ſome time held as captiue vnder feare, ſuffering my ſelfe vnwiſely to be carried away with their opinion, who thinke it ſafeſt to ſway with the time, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue with the Doctors, and to liue with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; to giue the heart to God, and the body to the world. <hi>I was dumbe, and ſayd nothing, I kept ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>euen from good: but my anguiſh increaſed, my heart waxed hot within me, and the fire kindled in my meditation, wherefore I ſpeake with my tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if heretofore the ſonne of King <hi>Croeſus</hi> beganne to ſpeake, ſeeing his Father in danger: Who will thinke it ſtrange, to ſee my tongue loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a ſubiect, where it haſtens to ſet forth the glory of God my eternall Father, and the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mine owne ſoule?</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1956:3"/>
            <p>For, <hi>With the heart we beleeue, but with the mouth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>wee confeſſe to ſaluation:</hi> for which cauſe Ieſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That whoſoeuer ſhall confeſſe him before</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 32. 33</note> 
               <hi>men, he will confeſſe him before his Father which is in heauen; But whoſoeuer ſhall deny him before men, him will he deny before his Father which is in heauen.</hi> And the Apoſtle alſo ſaith; <hi>Come out from amongſt them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 17.</note> (meaning from Idolaters) <hi>and ſeparate your ſelues, and touch no vncleane thing.</hi> And the Spirit of God <hi>Apoc. 18. Goe out of Babylon my people, left yee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of her ſins, and that yee receiue not of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God will haue no ſocietie with Satan, nor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the world; he will not with the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot haue his childe diuided; he will haue all, or <note place="margin">1 King. 3. 26.</note> nothing. <hi>For what hath righteouſneſſe to doe with iniquitie?</hi> And <hi>what communion hath light with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>darkeneſſe?</hi> Or <hi>what agreement hath Chriſt with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial?</hi> Or <hi>what portion hath the beleeuer with the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del?</hi> Or <hi>the Temple of God with Idols?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I called that to minde which God heretofore ſaid vnto the Iſraelites, by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Eliah, How long halt ye betweene two</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King. 18.</note> 
               <hi>opinions? If God be God follow him, but if Baal, follow him.</hi> I haue aduiſedly conſidered of what great validitie that Maxime, of our Sauiour is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>That it is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 24.</note> 
               <hi>impoſſible to ſerue two maſters;</hi> and haue often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that to minde which we reade <hi>Mat. 11. That the kingdome of heauen ſuffers violence, and the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent take it by force.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue often conſidered that God will haue his children marked, not onely with an inward ſeale, <note place="margin">Ephe. 1. 13.</note> but alſo with the marke of an outward profeſſion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1956:4"/> and that is the cauſe why in the 1. booke of <hi>Kings,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King. 19. 18.</note> Chapter 19. God ſaith hee had reſerued to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſeuen thouſand men (not onely who had not beleeued in the Idolatries of <hi>Baal,</hi> but) who had not bowed the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> nor kiſſed him. And in the ſeuenth Chapter of th' Apocalyps, v. 3. <hi>Iohn</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reu. 7. 3.</note> beheld in a Viſion an Angel, hauing the ſeale of the liuing God, to marke the ſeruants of God in their foreheads: teaching vs therein, that if wee will be reputed the ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt, wee muſt openly make profeſſion of the Truth, the which himſelfe teacheth vs in S. <hi>Iohn. If any one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 12. 26.</note> 
               <hi>ſerueth me, let him follow me. For he that is not with me, is againſt me, and he that gathereth not with me,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 30.</note> 
               <hi>ſcattereth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue alſo often thought with my ſelfe that the Deuill demanded nothing of Ieſus Chriſt, but what the worldly wiſe giue vnto him. For the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill hauing ſhewed Ieſus Chriſt all the kingdomes of the world, and the glory thereof, ſaith, <hi>All theſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4. 8.</note> 
               <hi>things will I giue thee</hi> (not if thou beleeue in me, but) <hi>if thou ſhalt fall downe and worſhip me. Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar</hi> required nothing of thoſe three wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies which were caſt into the fiery Furnace, but <note place="margin">Dan. 3. 15.</note> outwardly to worſhip his Image; and the greateſt tyrants not being able to diſcerne the thoughts of the heart, content themſelues with the bodie and the tongue.</p>
            <p>Yea, I thought, that if it ſufficed to beleeue the truth, without making profeſſion of it, in vaine ſhould ſo many Martyrs haue maintained it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Iudges, and confeſſed it in the very
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1956:4"/> flames, ſigned with their bloud, and ſealed with their death.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the Church on earth, is like vnto <hi>Iſrael</hi> in Egypt, and <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons den, and that in the eyes of the world, it is nothing but weakneſſe, and as it were a few Lambes in the midſt of a multitude of Wolues, if it ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it ſelfe to the times, there would neuer bee any Church. And in withdrawing our ſelues from the houſe of God, we ſhall not onely run into the Temples of Papiſts, but alſo into the Temples of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> ſaying by way of excuſe, <hi>yet I beleeue it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſon it ſelfe hath taught me, that it ſufficeth not a childe to haue a good conceit of his Father, vnleſſe he defend his quarrell, and that it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for a ſouldier to loue his Captaine, if hee fight not vnder his enſigne, and that ſhee is but a ſtrumpet, who vnder pretence of keeping her hart to her husband, proſtitutes her body to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; as alſo that it is the propertie of Baſtard children to be afraide to call themſelues by the name of their father: we are vnworthie the ſeruice of ſo great a King, if we be aſhamed to weare his Liuery, for ſuch a baſe ſeruant can neuer ſerue ſo rich a maſter.</p>
            <p>In a word, I haue conſidered, that God puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſinners more ſeuerely in his wrath, then <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 18.</note> ſuch <hi>as withhold his truth in vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi> and I haue oft trembled at the hearing of theſe words ſpoken by Ieſus Chriſt to the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reu. 3. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>I would thou wert either cold or hot; but becauſe thou
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1956:5"/> art neither cold nor hot, but luke-warme, I will ſpew thee out of my mouth.</hi> And thence it is, that I haue bin terrified with that horrible threat which God pronounceth in <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21. againſt ſuch as feare man more then God, and the ſeruant, rather then the Maiſter, for not onely to vnbeleeuers, abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, murtherers, whoremongers, ſorcerers, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and all lyars, <hi>But alſo vnto the fearefull, is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reu. 21. 8.</note> 
               <hi>lake of fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi> Nay, were it that God threatned vs not at all with ſuch terrible puniſhments, yet ought wee to be aſhamed, hauing receiued ſo many mercies from him, to repay him with ſo horrible ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; it being monſtrous, that ſuch who make Conſcience to ſteale from other men their goods, ſhould yet dare to defile themſelues with ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>For there is not a worſe ſacriledge, then to rob God of his glory, and he is worthie to be branded for a double dealer, who denies vnto God that iuſt defence of his cauſe which he owes vnto him.</p>
            <p>This is it then I haue conſidered with my ſelfe: Ieſus Chriſt is not aſhamed to call me his brother, <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 11.</note> and ſhould I be aſhamed to confeſſe my ſelfe to be his ſeruant? He hath not ſpared to ſhed his bloud for me, and ſhould I ſpare to ſpeake for his truth? He died for my ſaluation, and ſhould I not liue to his glory?</p>
            <p>I concluded then, that ſeeing he meant to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie my ſoule and bodie in heauen, it is juſt and reaſonable, that in ſoule and bodie I glorifie him on earth: according to the exhortion of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1956:5"/> 
               <hi>Ye are bought for a price, glorifie God then in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 20.</note> 
               <hi>your bodie, and in your spirit, for they are Gods.</hi> And yet I muſt tell you that God hath not ſetled me in this reſolution, but through many conflicts. For the fleſh to weaken my ſaith, was readie to rocke <note place="margin">Iud. 16. 15.</note> me aſleepe in her lap: and this fleſh, a ſworne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, that ſhee might ſtill retaine me in her bonds, and hinder me from aſcending the mountaine of ſaluation, cauſed me to looke backe towards thoſe <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> worldly profits which I was to abandon: ſhe told me that I ſhould breake the necke of all my For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes (as they are wont now adayes to ſpeake) and ſhould impriſon my ſelfe within the den of perpetuall ignominie, &amp; this obiection I confeſſe ſomewhat the more daunted me, being now come to thoſe yeares which naturally long for delights and thirſt after prayſes; the progreſſe in my ſtudies alſo hauing raiſed me vpon the ſteps which lead to honours, whereunto the fauour of my friends ſeemed to haue made a way open for me.</p>
            <p>But againe I thought, that this was a ſleight of the great Harlot, which to retaine me ſtill in the filthineſſe of her abominations, meant (euen like <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife, who inticed <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery with her) to hold me by the cloke, through the conſideration of earthly commodities; and therefore I choſe rather to leaue my cloke with <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> then to forſake mine innocencie, or to make any breach in my Conſcience.</p>
            <p>I conſidered, that all the riches and honours of this world, are turned to wormewood, to him that feares not God, and that all the pleaſures of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1956:6"/> fleſh, are but like to the Bees, which haue honey in their mouth, but ſtings in their tayle: the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning ſeemes pleaſing, but the end lamentable, for after a ſhort laughter, and a few fond delights in this life, followes eternall death, where ſhall be endleſſe weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>I alſo conſidered, that God hauing created man, to be Lord of the whole world, man ſhould not yeeld himſelfe as a vaſſall or ſlaue to ſuch vile creatures; That the whole world is not a portion worthy of the children of this great King: That God hath not indewed me with an immortall ſoule to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in the things, which haue but onely the dignitie to be mortall: That my ſoule being of an heauenly nature, ought to mount aboue all theſe terreſtrial things, and to aſpire to thoſe things that are aboue.</p>
            <p>In a word, I concluded that I ſhould make but an ill match of it, to win the whole world, if for <note place="margin">Man. 8. 38.</note> it I ſhould loſe my ſoule, and that it would proue but a meane comfort to goe to hell, laden with many Tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe I gaue my ſelfe to meditate on the ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>Thou careſt and art troubled about</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 10. 41.</note> 
               <hi>many things, but one thing is needfull:</hi> I gaue heed likewiſe to the exhortation of our Sauiour in S. <hi>Mathew,</hi> Chap. 6. <hi>Firſt ſeeke the kingdome of God,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 33.</note> 
               <hi>and his righteouſneſſe, and all theſe things ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto you.</hi> And that of S. <hi>Iohn, Labour not for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 6. 27.</note> 
               <hi>the meate that periſheth, but for that which endureth to eternall life.</hi> I taſted alſo the vertue of <hi>Pauls</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall words, 1 Tim. 6, <hi>Godlineſſe with contentment</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. 7.</note>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1956:6"/> 
               <hi>is great gaine. For we brought nothing into this world, and it is certaine we ſhall carrie nothing out. Therefore hauing food and rayment, let vs therewith be content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe Examples haue often the force of inſtructions, I ſet before me the Prophet <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 24. 25. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Who being come to age, refuſed to be called the ſonne of Pharaohs daughter: chooſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon. Eſteeming the rebuke of Chriſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter riches, then the treaſures of Egypt, for he had an eye to the recompence of reward.</hi> I muſed on the writings of <hi>Dauid,</hi> wherein he glorieth more, that hee was Gods ſeruant, then that hee was King of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> preferring the houſe of God, before his Palace Royall. As alſo I thought on the ſaying of that excellent Prince, the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who preferred his being a Citizen in the houſe of God, before all the glory of his Empire. But aboue all me thought I was wonderfully rauiſhed in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who had bin brought vp at the feete of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> who vnderſtood the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of Sciences, and ſpake the language of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; who had whereof to boaſt as concerning the fleſh, hauing all the aduantages his Nation affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and yet he cryeth out, Phil. 3. <hi>That which was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>gaine vnto me, I eſteemed loſſe for Chriſt; Yea, I haue counted all things to be loſſe vnto me for the excellent knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt my Lord. For whoſe ſake I haue depriued my ſelfe of all things, and doe iudge them to be dung, that I may winne Chriſt.</hi> The like is ſayd of all the Apoſtles, who vſe this ſpeech to Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>We haue leſt all, and followed thee.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1956:7"/>
            <p>And that which moſt comforted me, was the anſwere of our Sauiour, <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you, that whoſoeuer hath forſaken houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother for my ſake, and the Goſpels, ſhall receiue an hundred folde as much, and ſhall inherite e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore euen as the Apoſtles forſooke their Nets to follow Ieſus Chriſt; I alſo put from me theſe vaine cares, and the deceitfull hopes which intangled my minde, and with the royall Prophet I concluded, O Lord, thou art my porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 55.</note> I haue determined to keepe thy law. And that as Chriſt ſaith, Thoſe are bleſſed which heare the <note place="margin">Luke 11. 28.</note> word of God and keepe it; As alſo with <hi>Mary, I haue choſen the good part, which ſhall not bee taken</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 10. 42.</note> 
               <hi>from me.</hi> I ſayd in my ſelfe, what though I poſſeſſe not great things here on earth, yet ſhall I bee rich in thee, and an inheritour of the kingdome, which God hath promiſed to thoſe that loue him; I ſhall poſſeſſe that pearle of inualuable price, to wit, the knowledge of the Goſpell, and the graces of the Spirit, I ſhall be adorned with Ieſus Chriſt, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Iſrael, and the glory of our hope. And I ſhall obtaine a treaſure in heauen, where the moth corrupteth nor, and where theeues neither breake <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 20.</note> through, nor ſteale; If I lacke honor among mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men, God will ſingle me out as among his <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 17. 1 Pet. 2. 9.</note> moſt precious Iewels; I ſhall enter into the royall Prieſthood, and I may boaſt, that I am deſcended of the moſt auncient nobilitie that may be, ſeeing the titles of Gods houſe and familie are more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient then heauen and earth: and if I forſake
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1956:7"/> worldly pleaſures, I ſhall haue ſpirituall gladnes; I ſhall reioyce in God my Sauiour, with a Ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 8.</note> and glorious: and as <hi>Dauid</hi> taking his flight into the Deſerts, comforted himſelfe in the expectation of the kingdome which God had promiſed him; ſo, will I comfort my ſelfe in look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thoſe eternall felicities, which God hath reſerued for me among the Angels. To be ſhort, if with Ieſus Chriſt I haue not whereon to reſt my head, I will reioyce that in Ieſus Chriſt I haue peace of Conſcience: that God is the portion of <note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 5.</note> mine heritage, and of my Cup alwayes. O Lord <note place="margin">Pſal. 84. 1.</note> of hoſts, how amiable are thy dwelling places! my foule ceaſeth not, greatly to long, yea, euen fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth for the courts of the Lord, my heart and my fleſh reioyce in the liuing God. For a day in thy <note place="margin">Verſe 10.</note> Courts, is better then a thouſand elſe-where, I had rather be a doore-keeper in the houſe of my God, then to dwell in the tents of wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now if my fleſh were loth to forſake her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, ſhee thought it yet more ſtrange to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take her ſelfe vnto ſuch an vnpleaſing condition: ſhee thought it folly and madneſſe to enter into a path all paued with thornes, and filled with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions: ſhe ſet before me the reproch of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, but eſpecially in theſe woefull times, in which pietie is hereſie, and wherein it is counted a diſhonour to ſerue Chriſt. But according to the Apoſtles example, I ſhooke off this Viper, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">Act. 28.</note> taking any hurt, I beleeued that I ought to contemne this contempt, according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpell of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1956:8"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt, ſeeing it is the power of God to ſaluation to all that beleeue.</hi> I thought it better to ſhare with Gods children in the words reproach, then to be had in execration before God and his Angels, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to be made the ofſcouring of the earth, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo I might be made heauens delight.</p>
            <p>I thought it folly to imagine I ſhould reape, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had ſowed, to ouercome without conflict, and to be crowned, before I had run my race to the end, and that it is impoſſible to partake of the excellencie of Chriſts croſſe, without feeling the weight of it, ſeeing the paſchall Lambe was to be <note place="margin">Exod. 12. 8.</note> eaten with ſoure herbs, and the bread of the Lord, like that of <hi>Boaz,</hi> muſt be eaten with dipping it in <note place="margin">Ruth. 2.</note> vineger.</p>
            <p>I conſider, that ſeeing the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt is not of this world, it were extreame foliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in me, to ſeeke the world in his kingdome, or to thinke of reſt in his kingdome, who is the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of our Father, or not to make profeſſion of the Goſpell til perſecutions be ended, or to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs Ieſus Chriſt without his Croſſe, or a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell without reproach. To tarry till God had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out a new way to heauen, and till the worlde and Satan ſhould ceaſe to bee; for the enmitie of the old Serpent, which began in the earthly Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> will neuer haue an ende, till wee become to the heauenly,</p>
            <p>I alſo thought that ther is no afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell which Ieſus Chriſt hath not fore-told, &amp; that ſuch as are enrolled for ſeruants in his armie, muſt accept it vpon condition, that <hi>whoſoeuer will come</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 9. 23.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1956:8"/> 
               <hi>after me, muſt deny himſelfe, and take vp his Croſſe, and follow me.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt tels vs that if we will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 23.</note> into life eternall, wee muſt paſſe through the ſtraight gate, and this is that aduantage which in this life he tels his Apoſtle he muſt take for his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, <hi>I will ſhew him how many things hee muſt ſuffer for my ſake.</hi> A leſſon which the Apoſtle ſets vs <note place="margin">Act. 9. 16.</note> al to take out, ſaying; <hi>By many afflictions we muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 14. 22.</note> 
               <hi>into the kingdome of heauen,</hi> and <hi>2. Tim. 3. All that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus, muſt ſuffer perſecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhake of delicacie, when I caſt mine eyes vpon <hi>Daniel,</hi> who choſe rather to be caſt into the Lyons den, then to giue ouer lifting vp his hands to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: vpon thoſe three worthies, who choſe rather to bee expoſed to the mercy of the fiery furnace, then to bow before an Idol, and vppon ſo many cloudes of witneſſes, who were willing rather to ſhed their blood, then defile themſelues with Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie.</p>
            <p>And aboue all I was aſtonied in <hi>beholding Ieſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt the author and finiſher of our faith who for the ioy that was ſet before him endured the croſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the ſhame:</hi> For, <hi>the ſeruant is not greater then his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 13. 16.</note> 
               <hi>maſter, nor the Ambaſſader greater then hee that ſent him.</hi> Seeing our head was crowned with thornes, and was offered vinegar to drinke, all ſtreaming ouer with blood, what a vile ſhame is it for vs his members, to deſire the enioying of all our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties heere below in this corruptible world, or to lie ſucking at the breaſts of the poyſonful ſweets ther of yea, for as much as Ieſus Chriſt hath ſuffered ſo much for our ſaluation, is it not iuſt &amp; equall that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1956:9"/> wee prepare our ſelues to ſuffer for his glory, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that exhortation of the Apoſtle let <hi>vs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 13.</note> 
               <hi>goe forth out of the campe, bearing his reproach?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For I alſo thought, that to eſcape a theefe in the way, I ought not to caſt my ſelf headlong into infinite and ineuitable miſeries. For what corzie is more ſencible and intollerable, then that of an euill conſcience? yea, all the tortures in this life, are but light flea-bitings in reſpect of thoſe eternal puniſhments, wherewith God will puniſh thoſe, <hi>who worſhip the beaſt &amp; his Image, and whoſoeuer they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reu. 14. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>be that receiue the marke of the beaſt in their foreheads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which did yet fortifie mee moſt of all, was the conſolation which the Apoſtle giues vs, ſaying in his Epiſtle to the Romanes: <hi>That all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 28.</note> 
               <hi>thinges worke together for good to thoſe that loue God. That by afflictions, we are made conformable to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 29.</note> 
               <hi>of the Sonne of God:</hi> and that all <hi>our ſufferings</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 18.</note> 
               <hi>of this preſent life, being well weighed, are not worthie of the glory which is to come, and ſhall in due time bee reuealed vnto vs, For our light affliction which is but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 17.</note> 
               <hi>for a moment, works in vs a farre more excellent and eternall weight of glory, whilſt wee looke vpon, not the things which are ſeene, but on the things which are not ſeene, which are eternall. For thoſe who are come out of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reu. 7. 14.</note> 
               <hi>great tribulation, and haue waſhed their long robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lambe, that ſtand</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> 
               <hi>before the throne of God, and ſerue him day and night in his Temple, ſhall haue no more hunger, nor thirſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">16.</note> 
               <hi>the ſunne ſhall not light vpon them, nor any heat, for the Lambe which is in the midſt of the throne, ſhall feede</hi> 
               <note place="margin">17.</note> 
               <hi>them, and leade them to the fountaines of liuing waters,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1956:9"/> and God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes.</hi> That was it which cauſed me to change my note, and to thinke nothing ſweeter then the waters of <hi>Mara,</hi> when Chriſt our true <hi>Moſes</hi> caſts into them the wood of his Croſſe, aſſuring vs of the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit of his death and paſſion: yea, I dare ſay, that afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the name of Chriſt doe bring with them more true ioy and comfort to the faithfull ſoule, then the whole world furniſhed with all her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments to a prophane wretch. And therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are they who are perſecuted for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 10.</note> 
               <hi>righteouſneſſe ſake, for theirs is the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Bleſſed are ye when men reuile you, and perſecute</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 11.</note> 
               <hi>you and ſhall ſay all manner of euill ſaying againſt you falſely, for my names ſake, reioyce and be glad, for great</hi> 
               <note place="margin">12.</note> 
               <hi>is your reward in heauen, for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you.</hi> That is it which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> alſo ſaith in his Epiſtle, <hi>My brethren</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>thinke it perfect ioy when you fall into diuers tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> And that likewiſe of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> reioyce in as <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 13.</note> much as yee are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings, that when his glory ſhall appeare, yee may be glad and reioyce: If ye be railed vpon for the name of Chriſt, bleſſed are ye, for the ſpirit of glory and of God reſteth vpon you. Thence it is that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the <hi>Acts</hi> went away reioycing, that they <note place="margin">Act. 5. 41.</note> were counted worthie to ſuffer rebuke for the name of Ieſus Chriſt. And that the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> who had been rapt vp into the third heauen, and had heard words which are vnexpreſſable, which is not poſſible for man to vtter, choſe yet rather to reioyce in his ſufferings. The ioy which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1956:10"/> he for a time poſſeſſed among the Angels, being no let vnto him to reioyce in the middeſt of the Martyrs. <hi>I take pleaſure</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in reproches, in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 10.</note> 
               <hi>neceſſities, in perſecutions, in anguiſhes for Chriſt, for when I am weake, then I am ſtrong.</hi> From thence it came, that out of the middeſt of his moſt inward paſſions, he cries out, <hi>I am filled with conſolation,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 4.</note> 
               <hi>I am full with ioy more and more in all our affliction,</hi> for full well he knew, <hi>that it is freely giuen vs for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt, not onely to bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eue in him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore according to Chriſt his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, I beleeued that I ought not to feare thoſe <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 28.</note> who hauing killed the bodie, can doe no more, but to feare him rather, who can deſtroy both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule in hell fire, and that, if the ſufferings <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 5.</note> of Chriſt abound in vs, the conſolations of Chriſt ſhall abound in vs alſo. If we die with Chriſt, that <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 12.</note> we ſhall alſo liue with him. That if we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo raigne with him. And that if <note place="margin">Mar. 8. 35.</note> any will ſaue his life, he ſhall loſe it, and whoſoeuer ſhall loſe his life for Chriſts ſake, and the Goſpels, he ſhall ſaue it.</p>
            <p>And no maruaile if neither the threats nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the world preuailed with me, to hinder me from giuing glory to God, ſeeing the world can promiſe nothing which is more excellent then the kingdome of heauen, nor threaten any thing more terrible then the paines of hell: But as with a ſtedſaſt eye I looked vpon the world, which I now forſake, and the croſſe which I embrace: ſoon the other ſide, when I come to caſt mine
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1956:10"/> eyes vpon you (moſt honoured Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) and to ſet before me your tender affections, and paternall loues; whilſt I call to minde with what mildneſſe you brought me vp; what care you had of my education, ſparing no coſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct me in the knowledge of good letters, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming my mind to the loue of vertue: and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, when I thought how much affliction and diſcomfort my departing would bring vnto you in following a Religion, the excellencie whereof you yet diſcerne not.</p>
            <p>All theſe things I ſay well weighed, ſo wrought vpon mine affections, that it hath cauſed floods of teares to fall from mine eyes, and to be brought as it were to nothing, for the truth is, my loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you is ſo ardent and reſpectiue, that if it were but to endure any temporall puniſhments, I had rather ſuffer a thouſand torments and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, then to breed you the leſt diſcontentment: yea, I ingenuouſly confeſſe, that this conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo farre preuailed with me, that it had in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtayed me from proceeding on in this faire path, wherein I now walke, if God (hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of mine infirmitie) had not drawne me on by the hand of his grace, and ſtrengthened my weakeneſſe, to hearken to the words of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; <hi>Who ſo loueth father or mother more then me, is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 37.</note> 
               <hi>not worthie of me:</hi> As alſo to that anſwere which he made him which ſaid, <hi>I will follow thee Lord,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 9. 61.</note> 
               <hi>but firſt giue me leaue to take leaue of thoſe that are at mine houſe; None that putteth his hand to the plough,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and looketh backe, is fit for the kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1956:11"/>
            <p>Then I conſidered, that God called me to the ſame condition vnto which he called the Father of the faithfull, <hi>Goe out of the countrie, and from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 12. 1.</note> 
               <hi>thy kindred, and from thy Fathers houſe, to goe into a countrie which I will ſhew thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thought that, if I was bound to reſpect the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of my body, I was much more bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Father of my ſpirit, and that it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obey God then men. <note place="margin">Act. 4. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And the better to alay this bitternes, I comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe the ſweetnes of the gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of my good God, <hi>I will receiue you, and will be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 18.</note> 
               <hi>a father vnto you, and you ſhalbe my ſonnes, and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſaith the Lord Almighty, 2. Cor. 6.</hi> Whence I came to conclude thus with my ſelfe, I forſake my fathers houſe, but I enter into the houſe of God, I eſtrange my ſelfe from my naturall parents but I enter into that high and noble alliance and ſpirituall kindred which is named in heauen and in earth, of which Ieſus Chriſt is the head. <hi>When</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3. 15. Pſal. 27. 10.</note> 
               <hi>my father and my mother forſake me, the Lord will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther me vp.</hi> Add alſo, that with this conſolation I comforted my ſelfe thus, namely, that I entred not into a Church which vnder pretence of piety tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth me to caſt off the bands of naturall reſpects and dutie, but which commands all Chriſtians to nouriſh within them the cordial affections of true <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> charitie inſtructing children to honour their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother in all things, in the Lord. The <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> honour and loue which I owe you, are too faſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graued in my breaſt, to be blotted out. The bands wherwith I am knit vnto you, are too ſtrong to be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1956:11"/> broken, and my deſire to acknowledge your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours ſhall neuer die in me, till I die.</p>
            <p>Now I nothing doubt but you will witnes with me how blameleſſe my conuerſation was during the time I conuerſed amongſt you, I was alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with a moſt ardent affection to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto you, that it was neither raſhnes nor lightnes, which cauſed mee to change Religion. But I onely ſuffered my ſelfe to be vanquiſhed by the power of truth, &amp; the motions of Gods holy Spirit: to which purpoſe you know I endeuoured my ſelfe in your preſence to maintaine this truth agaiuſt ſuch Doctors as you approued of, (which I often did in particuler conferences (hauing lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>that God perfects his prayſe by the mouth of babes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and perfects his power in our weakeneſſe. For as God hides his ſecrets from the wiſe and prudent, &amp; reueales</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 9.</note> 
               <hi>them vnto little ones,</hi> So hath the Truth greater <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 25.</note> force in the mouth of a childe, then a lye in the mouth of all the Doctors in the worlde. But the miſeries of theſe times not permitting me to enter into ſuch diſputes, without expoſing my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to manifeſt danger, and not minding to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Church of GOD through trouble: As alſo that diſputations now adayes are rather lowd then fruitfull: becauſe they diſpute onely to diſpute, ſtriuing rather for victory then truth, I thought it euery way better, and more to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſet downe my reaſons of this my alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and change by writing: to which the grace of God aſſiſting me, I will without ceaſing ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, now that God of his mercy hath giuen mee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1956:12"/> to arriue in ſuch a place, where it is lawfull both to ſpeake and write the truth. For I hold my ſelfe ſtill bound to giue you an account of my procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and I ſhould thinke my ſelfe happy, if this little light which God hath communicated vnto me, might ſomething enlighten your darkeneſſe, then ſhould I willingly yeelde my Spirit to God that gaue it, if I might ſee you with my ſelfe walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the way to life and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>In expectation whereof I beſeech the great God and father of mercies, that hee will make vs all mind one and the ſame thing in Chriſt, that he will repleniſh you with the ioyes and comforts of his holy Spirit, granting vs all the grace, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wee haue glorified him a little while heere on earth, wee may be glorified with him for euer in heauen, euen with that glory which hee hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs before the foundation of the world.</p>
            <p>So prayeth he who craues that you will alwayes beleeue it, euen vnto the altar.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble, moſt affectionate,</hi> and moſt obedient Sonne, de VRILLAC.</signed>
               <dateline>From SEDAN, <date>this 3. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1621.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1956:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
